当使用LLM构建复杂应用程序时，
When building a complex application using an LLM,
一个重要但有时有点棘手的步骤是
one of the important but sometimes tricky steps is
如何评估应用程序的表现？
how do you evaluate how well your application is doing?
它是否达到了某种验收标准？
Is it meeting some accuracy criteria?
此外，如果你决定换一种实现方式，
And also, if you decide to change your implementation,
可能换到不同的LLM，
maybe swap in a different LLM
或者更改如何使用向量数据库的策略，或者使用其他方式检索数据，
or change the strategy of how you use a vector database or something else to retrieve channels,
或者更改系统中的其他参数。
or change some other parameter to the system.
你要怎么样知道结果是比以前更好了？还是更糟糕了？
How do you know if you're making it better or worse?
在这个视频中，Harrison将深入探讨一些框架，以思考如何评估基于LLM的应用程序，
In this video, Harrison will dive into some frameworks to how to think about evaluating a LLM based application,
同时会介绍一些帮助你评估的工具。
as well as some tools that help you do that.
这些应用实际上是许多不同步骤的链和序列。
These applications are really chains and sequences of a lot of different steps.
我们的首要任务是
And so honestly, part of the first thing that you should do is
了解每个步骤的输入和输出到底是什么。
just understand what exactly is going in and coming out of each step.
因此，我们会用到一些可视化工具和调试工具。
And so some of the tools can really just be thought of as visualizers or debuggers in that thing.
使用大量不同的数据集来测试模型，这有助于我们全面了解模型的表现。
But it's often really useful to get a more holistic picture on a lot of different data points of how the model is doing.
观察事物的一种方法是用肉眼看。
And one way to do that is by looking at things by eye.
但还有一个非常酷的想法，就是使用语言模型和链来评估其他语言模型、其他链和其他应用程序。
But there's also this really cool idea of using language models themselves and chains themselves to evaluate other language models and other chains and other applications.
我们也会深入探讨这个想法。
And we'll dive a bunch into that as well.
这个视频中有很多有趣的话题，
So lots of cool topics,
我发现随着越来越多的开发转向基于Prompt的开发，使用LLM开发应用程序，
and I find that with a lot of development shifting towards prompting-based development, developing applications using LLMs,
整个工作流程、评估过程正在被重新思考。
this whole workflow evaluation process is being rethought.
这个视频里有很多激动人心的概念。
So lots of exciting concepts in this video.
让我们开始吧。
Let's dive in.
好的，让我们开始设置评估所需要的环境。
All right, so let's get set up with evaluation.
首先，我们需要有一个链或应用程序，以便进行评估。
First, we need to have the chain or the application that we're going to evaluate in the first place.
我们将使用上一课的文档问答链。
And we're going to use the document question answering chain from the previous lesson.
所以我们要导入所需的相关库。
So we're going to import everything we need.
我们将加载上一课中使用过的相同数据。
We're going to load the same data that we were using.
我们将用一行代码创建索引。
We're going to create that index with one line.
然后，我们将通过指定语言模型、链类型、检索器以及verbosity（要打印日志的详细程度）这些参数来创建RetrievalQA链。
And then we're going to create the retrieval QA chain by specifying the language model, the chain type, the retriever, and then the verbosity that we're going to print out.
现在我们有了这个应用程序。
So we've got this application.
我们需要做的第一件事就是
And the first thing we need to do is
真正搞清楚我们需要用什么样的数据集来评估。
we need to really figure out what are some data points that we want to evaluate it on.
我将介绍几种不同的方法来实现这个目标。
And so there's a few different methods that we're going to cover for doing this.
第一个方法最简单，
The first is the most simple,
就是自己想出一些好的示例数据集。
which is basically we're going to come up with data points that we think are good examples ourselves.
为了做到这一点，我们可以查看一些数据并提出示例问题
And so to do that, we can just look at some of the data and come up with example questions
然后提供可以用于评估的标准答案。
and then example ground truth answers that we can later use to evaluate.
让我们看一下这里的几份文档，
So if we look at a few of the documents here,
可以了解到文档里面都有什么。
We can kind of get a sense of what's going on inside them.
看起来第一个文档是关于一套连帽衫的。
It looks like the first one, there's this pullover set.
第二个文档是关于一件夹克的，都有很多详细信息。
There's this in the second one, there's this jacket as a bunch of details about all of them.
从这些详细信息中，我们可以创建若干组示例问题和答案。
And from these details, we can create some example query and answer pairs.
第一个问题，我们可以简单地问：“舒适保暖连帽衫套装有侧口袋吗？”
So the first one, we can ask a simple, "Does the Cozy Comfort Pullover Set have side pockets?"
我们可以通过上面看到，它确实有侧口袋。
And we can see by looking above that it does, in fact, have some side pockets in it.
对于第二个，我们可以看到这件夹克来自某个系列，DownTek系列。
And then for the second one, we can see that this Jacket is from a certain collection, the DownTek collection.
所以我们可以问这个问题："这件夹克来自哪个系列？"
And so we can ask the question, "What collection is this jacket from?"
答案是："DownTek系列"。
And have the answer be, "The DownTek collection".
所以在这里我们创建了两组问答示例。
And so here we've created two examples.
但是，这种方式并不易于扩展。
But this doesn't really scale that well.
需要花费一些时间来查看每个示例，弄清楚发生了什么。
It takes a bit of time to look through each example and figure out what's going on.
那么有没有办法让我们自动化这个过程？
And so is there a way that we can automate it?
借助语言模型来自动化这个过程是一种非常酷的方式。
And one of the really cool ways that we think we can automate it is with language models themselves.
在LangChain中有一个链可以做到这一点。
So we have a chain in LangChain that can do exactly that.
我们可以导入QAGenerationChain
So we can import the QAGenerationChain
它可以读取文档并从每个文档中生成一组问题和答案。
and this will take in documents and it will create a question answer pair from each document.
它将借助语言模型来实现。
It'll do this using a language model itself.
因此，我们需要通过传入ChatOpenAI语言模型来创建这个链。
So we need to create this chain by passing in the ChatOpenAI language model.
然后我们可以用它创建很多组问题和答案示例。
And then from there, we can create a bunch of examples.
我们将使用apply_and_parse方法，应用解析器来解析输出的结果。
And so we're going to use the apply_and_parse method, because this is applying an output parser to the result.
因为我们想要得到一系列包含一组问题和答案的字典对象，而不是一个文本字符串。
Because we want to get back a dictionary that has the query and answer pair, not just a single string.
现在如果我们看一下返回的内容，
And so now if we look at what exactly is returned here,
我们可以看到一个问题和一个答案。
we can see a query and we can see an answer.
让我们检查一下这是哪个文档的问题和答案。
And let's check the document that this is a question and answer for.
我们可以看到它在问这个的重量是多少。
And we can see that it's asking what the weight of this is.
我们可以看到它是从这里获取重量的。
We can see that it's taking the weight from here.
看看这个，
And look at that.
我们刚刚生成了很多组问题和答案，
We just generated a bunch of question answer pairs.
不需要去一个个手动生成。
We didn't have to write it all ourselves.
这样可以帮我们节省很多时间，可以去做更多其他有意思的事情。
Saves us a bunch of time and we can do more exciting things.
现在让我们把这些示例加入到我们已经创建的示例中。
And so now let's go ahead and add these examples into the examples that we already created.
现在我们有了这些示例数据，但是我们如何评估效果如何？
So we got these examples now, but how exactly do we evaluate what's going on?
首先，我们要做的就是将其中某个示例传入链并运行，然后观察它输出的结果。
The first thing we want to do is just run an example through the chain and take a look at the output it produces.
这里我们输入一个问题，然后得到返回结果。
So here we pass in a query and we get back.
但我们无法观察到链的内部到底发生了什么！
but this is a little bit limiting in terms of what we can see that's actually happening inside the chain.
例如传给语言模型中的Prompt是什么？
What is the actual prompt that's going into the language model?
它检索到的文档有哪些？
What are the documents that it retrieves?
如果这是一个包含多个步骤的复杂链，那么每一步的中间结果是什么？
If this were a more complex chain with multiple steps in it, what are the intermediate results?
仅仅观察最终答案通常不足以理解
It's oftentimes not enough to just look at the final answer to understand
链中哪里出错或可能出错。
what is or could be going wrong in the chain.
为了解决这个问题，LangChain中提供了一个有意思的小工具，叫做“langchain debug”。
And to help with that, we have a fun little util in LangChain called LangChain debug.
如果我们把 "langchain.debug" 设为 "True",
And so if we set "langchain.debug" equals "True",
然后把之前的示例再运行一遍，
and we now rerun the same example as above,
就可以看到它输出了更多的信息。
we can see that it starts printing out a lot more information.
如果我们看看它到底输出了什么，
And so if we look at what exactly it's printing out,
我们可以看到它首先调用了RetrievalQA链，
we can see that it's diving down first into the RetrievalQA chain.
然后它又调用了StuffDocumentsChain。
And then it's going down into a StuffDocumentsChain.
上一节课讲到过，我们使用了 "stuff" 方法。
And so as mentioned, we were using the "stuff" method.
现在它调用了LLMChain，有几个不同的输入参数：
And now it's entering the LLMChain where we have a few different inputs.
可以看到原始问题，
So we can see the original question is right there.
传入的上下文，
And now we're passing in this context.
可以看到这个上下文是根据问题检索到的几个文档块内容。
And we can see that this context is created from a bunch of the different documents that we've retrieved.
在做问答时，
And so when doing question answering,
往往当返回错误的结果时，不一定是语言模型本身出了问题。
oftentimes when a wrong result is returned, it's not necessarily the language model itself that's messing up.
实际上，可能是在检索的步骤出了问题。
It's actually the retrieval step that's messing up.
仔细查看问题的确切内容
And so taking a really close look at what exactly the question is
和上下文的确切内容可以帮助调试，找出问题在哪。
and what exactly the context is can help debug what's going wrong.
我们可以再深入一层，看看究竟传入语言模型（ChatOpenAI）的Prompt究竟是什么。
We can then step down one more level and see exactly what is entering the language model, ChatOpenAI, itself.
这里我们可以看到传入语言模型的完整Prompt：
And so here we can see the full prompt that's passed in.
有一个系统消息。
So we've got a system message.
有一个对Prompt的描述。
We've got the description of the prompt that's used.
这就是问答链在底层使用的Prompt，
And so this is the prompt that the question answering chain is using under the hood,
我们直到现在才看到。
which we actually haven't even looked at until now.
我们可以看到Prompt输出：“使用以下上下文信息来回答用户的问题，
And so we can see the prompt printing out, use the following pieces of context to answer the user's question.
如果你不知道答案，就说不知道，
If you don't know the answer, just say that you don't know.
不要试图编造答案。”
Don't try to make up an answer.
然后我们看到之前插入的一堆上下文。
And then we see a bunch of the context as inserted before.
接着我们看到一个人类提出的问题，这就是我们问它的问题。
And then we see a human question, which is the question that we asked it.
我们还可以看到更多语言模型返回的结果信息。
We can also see a lot more information about the actual return type.
所以不仅仅是一个字符串，我们还得到了诸如Token使用量这样的信息，
So rather than just a string, we get back a bunch of information like the token usage,
比如Prompt消耗了多少Token、返回的结果消耗了多少Token、总共消耗的Token数和模型名称。
so the prompt tokens, the completion tokens, total tokens, and the model name.
这些信息对于跟踪在链或调用语言模型中使用了多少Token非常有用，
And this can be really useful to track the tokens that you're using in your chains or calls to language models over time
根据消耗的Token数和模型，可以算出来花费了多少成本。
and keep track of the total number of tokens, which corresponds very closely to the total cost.
因为这是一个相对简单的链，
And because this is a relatively simple chain,
我们现在可以看到最后的返回结果：
we can now see that the final response,
“舒适保暖连帽衫套装，条纹款，有侧口袋。”，
"The Cozy Comfort Pullover Set, Stripe, does have side pockets.",
通过链传递并返回给用户。
is getting bubbled up through the chains and getting returned to the user.
我们刚刚讲解了如何查看和调试
So we've just walked through how to look at and debug
这个链中单个输入的情况。
what's going on with a single input to this chain.
但是如何输入我们前面创建的所有示例呢？
But what about all the examples we created?
我们该如何评估它们呢？
How are we going to evaluate those?
和创建示例数据的方法类似，一种方法是手动操作。
Similarly to when creating them, one way to do it would be manually.
我们可以在所有示例上运行链，
We could run the chain over all the examples,
然后观察输出，搞清楚发生了什么，是否正确、错误或部分正确。
then look at the outputs and try to figure out what's going on, whether it's correct, incorrect, partially correct.
与创建示例数据类似，手动操作的方法随着时间的推移会变得有些繁琐。
Similar to creating the examples, that starts to get a little bit tedious over time.
所以让我们回到大家最喜欢的解决方案。
And so let's go back to our favorite solution.
能让语言模型来完成吗？
Can we ask a language model to do it?
首先，我们需要为所有示例生成实际答案。
First, we need to create predictions for all the examples.
在此之前，
Before doing that,
我实际上要关闭调试模式，以免把所有内容都打印出来，
I'm actually going to turn off the debug mode in order to just not print everything out onto the screen,
然后我将为所有不同的示例生成实际答案。
and then I'm going to create predictions for all the different examples.
我想我们总共有七个示例，
And so I think we had seven examples total,
我们将循环七次，为每个示例生成一个实际答案。
and so we're going to loop through this chain seven times, getting a prediction for each one.
现在我们有了这些示例，可以考虑评估它们。
Now that we've got these examples, we can think about evaluating them.
我们将导入QAEvalChain。
So we're going to import the QA, question answering, eval chain.
我们将用语言模型创建这个链，
We are going to create this chain with a language model,
因为我们将使用语言模型来帮助评估。
because again, we're going to be using a language model to help do the evaluation.
然后我们将在这个链上调用"evaluate"方法。
And then we're going to call evaluate on this chain.
并传入示例列表和实际答案列表，
We're going to pass in examples and predictions,
然后我们将得到与这组示例列表相对应的一组评估打分结果，并保存到了"graded_outputs"变量。
and we're going to get back a bunch of graded outputs.
为了查看每个示例的具体情况，
And so in order to see what exactly is going on for each example,
我们将遍历它们。
we're going to loop through them.
我们要打印出问题。
We're going to print out the question.
再次说明，这是由语言模型生成的。
And again, this was generated by a language model.
我们要打印出标准答案。
We're going to print out the real answer.
同样，这是语言模型基于整个文档的内容生成的，
And again, this was also generated by a language model when it had the whole document in front of it.
所以它生成的标准答案是可靠的。
And so it could generate a ground truth answer.
我们要打印出实际答案。
We're going to print out the predicted answer.
这是在语言模型和问答链生成的，
And this is generated by a language model when it's doing the QA chain,
先对问题生成Embedding，然后去向量数据库检索相似文档，再将检索出来的文档传递给语言模型，
when it's doing the retrieval with the embeddings in the vector databases, passing that into a language model,
然后语言模型生成实际答案。
and then trying to guess the predicted answer.
我们还会打印出评分。
And then we're also going to print it out the grade.
再次强调，这也是由语言模型生成的
And again, this is also generated by a language model
评估链对标准答案和实际答案进行对比，判断对错，得出一个评分。
when it's asking the eval chain to grade what's going on and whether it's correct or incorrect.
所以当我们遍历所有这些示例并打印它们时，
And so when we loop through all these examples and print them out,
可以详细查看每个示例。
we can see those in detail for each example.
看起来每一个示例都做对了。
And looks like here it got everything correct.
这是一个相对简单的检索问题，所以这结果还是靠得住的。
This is a relatively simple retrieval problem, so that is reassuring.
那我们来看第一个示例。
So let's look at the first example.
这里的问题是：“舒适保暖套装有侧面口袋吗？”
The question here is, "Does the Cozy Comfort Pullover Set have side pockets?"
我们创建的标准答案是：“是的”。
The real answer, and we created this, is "Yes".
语言模型生成的实际答案是：
The predicted answer, which the language model produced, was,
“舒适保暖套装，条纹款确实有侧面口袋。”
"The Cozy Comfort Pullover Set, Stripe does have side pockets".
所以我们可以认为这个答案是正确的。
And so we can understand that this is a correct answer.
实际上，语言模型也知道，并且它把它标记为正确。
And actually the language model does as well and it creates it correct.
但让我们想想为什么我们需要使用语言模型。
But let's think about why we actually need to use the language model in the first place.
因为这两个字符串实际上一点都不像。
These two strings are actually nothing alike.
它们非常不同。
They're very different.
一个很短，一个很长。
One's really short, one's really long.
“是的”这个词在这个长字符串里都没有出现。
I don't even think "Yes" doesn't appear anywhere in this string.
所以如果我们试图进行字符串匹配、精确匹配或者使用正则表达式，
So if we were to try to do some string matching or exact matching or even some regexes here,
是无法对两个字符串进行比较的。
it wouldn't know what to do.
它们不是同一回事。
They're not the same thing.
这就突显了在这里使用语言模型进行评估的重要性。
And that shows off the importance of using the language model to do evaluation here.
你有这些答案，
You've got these answers.
它们可能是任意的字符串。
which are arbitrary strings.
答案不是唯一的，
There's no single one-truth string that is the best possible answer.
有很多不同的变体。
There's many different variants.
只要它们意思相同，
And as long as they have the same semantic meaning,
它们就应该被看做是相似的。
they should be graded as being similar.
这就是语言模型的作用，而不仅仅是进行精确匹配。
And that's what a language model helps with, as opposed to just doing exact matching.
之所以对语言模型的评估如此困难，就是因为很难对字符串进行比较。
This difficulty in comparing strings is what makes evaluation of language models so hard in the first place.
我们将语言模型用于这些非常开放的任务，让它们生成文本。
We're using them for these really open-ended tasks where they're asked to generate text.
这在模型上从来没有真正做过，直到最近模型变的足够好了，才好来做这个。
This hasn't really been done before as models until recently weren't really good enough to do this.
目前为止很多现存的评估指标都不够好。
And so a lot of the evaluation metrics that did exist up to this point just aren't good enough.
我们不得不发明新的指标和新的启发式方法。
and we're having to invent new ones and invent new heuristics for doing so.
目前最有趣和最受欢迎的启发式方法实际上是
And the most interesting and most popular of those heuristics at the moment is actually
使用语言模型进行评估。
using a language model to do the evaluation.
这节关于评估的课程到此就结束了，但我还想给你们展示一下LangChain的评估平台。
This finishes the evaluation lesson, but one last thing I want to show you is the LangChain evaluation platform.
借助评估平台可以在Notebook中完成我们刚做的所有事情，并且可以在UI中显示，并对数据持久化。
This is a way to do everything that we just did in the notebook, but persist it and show it in a UI.
那么让我们看看。
And so let's check it out.
在这里，可以看到有一个会话。
Here, we can see that we have a session.
我们称之为"deeplearningai"。
We called it "deeplearningai".
可以看到实际上已经保存了我们在Notebook中运行的所有记录。
And we can see here that we've actually persisted all the runs that we ran in the notebook.
这是一个跟踪输入和输出的好方法，
And so this is a good way to track the inputs and outputs at a high level,
也是一个查看底层究竟发生了什么的好方法。
but it's also a really good way to see what exactly is going on underneath.
这与我们在Notebook中打开调试模式时打印出的信息相同，
So this is the same information that was printed out in the notebook when we turned on debug mode,
但它在UI中以更好的方式呈现。
but it's just visualized in a UI in a little bit of a nicer way.
我们可以看到链的输入和每个步骤中链的输出。
And so we can see the inputs to the chain and the outputs to the chain at each step.
然后我们可以进一步深入链中，
And then we can click further and further down into the chain
了解更多实际传入的信息。
and see more and more information about what is actually getting passed in.
如果我们一直到最底层，
And so if we go all the way down to the bottom,
可以看到究竟向聊天模型传入了什么内容。
we can now see what's getting passed exactly to the chat model.
这里有系统消息。
We've got the system message here.
这里有人类的问题。
We've got the human question here.
这里有来自聊天模型的返回结果。
We've got the response from the Chat Model here.
还有一些元数据的输出。
And we've got some Output Metadata.
我们在这里添加的另一个功能是将这些示例添加到数据集中。
One other thing that we've added here is the ability to add these examples to a data set.
如果你还有印象的话，在一开始创建那些示例数据集时，
So if you remember, when creating those data sets of examples at the start,
我们是通过手工和语言模型部分创建的。
we created them partially by hand, partially with a language model.
我们可以通过点击这个小按钮将其添加到数据集中，
Here we can add it to a data set by clicking on this little button,
现在我们有了输入问题和输出结果。
and we now have the input query and the output results.
这样我们就可以创建一个数据集。
And so we can create a data set.
我们可以给它命名为"deeplearning"。
We can call it deep learning.
然后我们可以开始向这个数据集添加示例。
And then we can start adding examples to this data set.
回到我们在课程开始时解决的原始问题，
And so again, getting back to the original thing that we tackled at the beginning of the lesson,
我们需要创建这些数据集以便进行评估。
we need to create these data sets so that we can do evaluation.
这是一种在后台运行的好方法，
This is a really good way to have this just running in the background
然后随着时间的推移向示例数据集中添加内容并开始积累这些示例，
and then add to the example data sets over time and start building up these examples
这样你就可以开始将这些数据集用于评估，并让评估的飞轮开始转动起来。
that you can start using for evaluation and have this flywheel of evaluation start turning.